Trice, Harrison, Additional Books /4254
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Harrison Trice Additional Books
1960-1991
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation & Archives
Trice, Harrison M.
/4254
4 cubic feet
4 linear ft.
Records (documents).
Articles by Professor Trice and interview transcripts from a study on Employee Assistance Programs.
8059001
General
Contact Information:
Kheel Center for Labor-Management Documentation and Archives Martin P. Catherwood Library 227 Ives Hall Cornell University Ithaca, NY 14853 (607) 255-3183 kheel_center@cornell.edu http://www.ilr.cornell.edu/library/kheel-center
Compiled by:
Kheel Staff, January 28, 2014
EAD encoding:
Kheel Staff, March 04, 2019
Biographical / Historical
Harrison Miller Trice (May 25, 1920 December 5, 1994)
Harrison Miller Trice was Professor Emeritus in the Department of Organizational Behavior at the School of Industrial and Labor Relations, Cornell University, where he had been a member of the faculty since 1955. Professor Trice's major contribution to his discipline has been the integration of the study of alcohol and drugs with the study of the workplace. More than any other social scientist, he was responsible for integrating occupational and organizational sociology with the study of alcohol and drugs.
His courses on occupational culture, deviance in the workplace, and employee assistance programs were always popular. Until his retirement, he conducted a large course in which each student was required to carry out a specific field study. Among the most popular of these studies were those >concerned with alcohol and drugs. While committed to research and public policy, Harrison Trice was also committed to teaching.
Prior to his retirement from teaching in 1991, Professor Trice also played the pivotal role in securing an endowment to establish Cornell's R. Brinkley Smithers Institute for Alcohol- Related Workplace Studies at the School of Industrial and Labor Relations. After his retirement, he kept up an active research program, completing two books in 1993 on organizational culture-The Cultures of Work Organizations, co-authored with Professor Janice Beyer, and Occupational Subcultures in the Workplace. Both books have received great acclaim from reviewers. At the time of his death, he and Professor Paul Roman were revising Spirits and Demons at Work: Alcohol and Drugs on the Job, and he was co-editing with Professor Paul Steele a special issue of the Journal of Drug Issues on workplace programs for the prevention and treatment of alcohol and other drug problems.
In 1994, Professor Trice was the recipient of two awards which recognized his lifetime contributions to the field of alcohol and drug studies. In August, he received the Distinguished Career Award from the American Sociological Association's Drinking and Drugs Section. In November, he received an award from New York State's Office of Alcoholism and Substance Abuse Services for his many contributions to the area of employee assistance programs, particularly his efforts to deliver rigorous training and education programs to practitioners.
Scope and Contents
The first box contains a few articles by Professor Trice and documentation regarding interviews and interview analysis for a study on Employee Assistance Programs. The interviewees were EAP administrators, HR Directors, and EAP participants. The other three boxes contain transcripts of the interviews. The interviewees are identified in the transcripts my alpha-numeric codes, rather than by name.
Conditions Governing Access
Access to the collections in the Kheel Center is restricted. Please contact a reference archivist for access to these materials.
Related Materials
Related Collections: /3010: Harrison Trice Papers /4164: Harrison M. Trice Additional Papers /4164: Harrison M. Trice Additional Papers /4297: ILR School Biography Files /4313: Harrison Trice Papers /4321 AV: ILR School Smithers Institute Audio-Visual Materials 6007: U.S. Department of Labor Office of American Workplace Labor Management Cooperation Collected Publications
Alcoholism and employment; Employee assistance programs; Trice, Harrison Miller, 1920-; New York State School of Industrial and Labor Relations
8059001
- "The Assessment of Change in Training and Therapy", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  Belasco, James and Harrison M. Trice. New York: McGraw Hill, 1969. p. 100-113
- "Unanticipated Returns of Training", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  Belasco, James and Harrison M. Trice. Training and Development Journal. July 1969. p. 12 -17
- "The Communication of Power Relations in Organizations through Cultural Rites", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  Beyer, Janice M. and Harrison M. Trice. Inside Organizations. 1988. p. 141-157
- "How an Organizations' Rites Reveal its Cultural", 1987 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  Beyer, Janice M. and Harrison M. Trice. Organizational Dynamics. 1987. p. 5-24
- "On the Problem of Clarifying Commitment Theory", 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  Ritzer, George and Harrison Trice. Social Forces. 1970. p. 530-533
- "The Personnel Manager and his Self-Image", 1972 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  Ritzer, George and Harrison M. Trice. Personnel Administration, Jan. - Feb. 1972. p. 46-51
- "An Empirical Study of Howard Becker's Side-Bet Theory", 1969 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  Ritzer, George and Harrison Trice. Social Forces. Vol. 47, No. 4, June 1969. p. 475- 478
- "Comments and Discussion", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  Trice, Harrison M. Reframing Organizational Culture. 1991. p. 298308
- "Night Watchmen: A Study of an Isolated Occupation", 1964 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  Vol.10, No. 2. 1964. p. 3-8
- "Rites and Ceremonials in Organizational Cultures", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  Trice, Harrison M. Research in the Sociology of Organizations. Vol. 4, 1985. p. 221- 270
- "Rural-Reared Workers and Labor Turnover", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  Trice, Harrison M. Rural Sociology. Vol. 26, 1961. p. 299-304
- "The Role of Ceremonials in Organizational Behavior:, 1969 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  Trice, Harrison M., James Belasco, and Joseph A. Alutto. Industrial and Labor Relations Review. Oct. 1969, Vol. 23, No. 1. p. 40-51
- "The Ceremonial Effect: Manifest Function or Latent Dysfunction in the Dynamic Organization", 1983 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Janice M. Beyer. Organizational Folklore Conference. 1983. p. 1-21
- "Cultural Leadership in Organizations", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Janice M. Beyer. Organization Science. May 1991, Vol. 2, No. 2. p. 149-169
- "Employee Assistance Programs", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Janice M. Beyer. Research in Community and Mental Health. 1984, Vol. 4. p. 243-290
- "Studying Organizational Cultures through Rites and Ceremonials", 1984 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Janice M. Beyer. Academy of Management review. 1984, Vol. 9. No. 4. p. 653-669
- "Using Six Organizational Rites to Change Culture", 1985 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Janice M. Beyer. Gaining Control of Corporate Culture. 1985. p. 370-398
- "An Anthropological View of Conflict in Work Organizations", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  Trice, Harrison M. Annual Meeting of Academy of Management, Anaheim, CA. August 1988. p. 1-17
- "Cultural Diversity: Subcultures and Countercultures in Work Organizations", 1990 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  Trice, Harrison M. and David A. Morand. Organizational Sociology. Fall 1990. p. 1035
- "Rites of Passage in Work Careers" (Box 1, Folder 20)
  Trice, Harrison M. and David Morand. P. 397-416
- "Work Careers as Rites of Passage", 1986 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  Trice, Harrison M. and David A. Morand. Handbook of Career Theory. 1986. p. 1-30
- "Use of Application Blank Data in a Study of Job Quitting", 1961 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Robert V. Penfield. Summer 1961. p. 9-13
- "Evolution of Training: Strategy, Tactics and Problems", 1974 (Box 1, Folder 23)
  Trice, Harrison M. and Paul M. Roman. Training Information Sources. June 1974, No. 3. p. 1-45
- "Drinking Behavior and Risk Factors Related to the Workplace: Implications for Research and Prevention", 1988 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  Trice, Harrison M. and William J. Sonnenstuhl. Journal of Applied Behavioral Science. 1988, Vol. 24, No. 4. p. 327-341
- "Organizations and Types of Occupational Communities", 1991 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  Sonnenstuhl, William J. and Harrison M. Trice. Research in the Sociology of Organizations. 1991, Vol. 9. p. 295-314
- Employee Attitudes Toward Performance Appraisal, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 26)
  Stafford, Helen R., Marie E. Knickrehm, and Harrison M. Trice. Journal of the American Dietetic Association. Jan. 1966, Vol. 48, No. 1. p. 20-24
- Smithers' Endowment Proposal Transcription, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  Fall/Winter 1988 - 1989
- Syracuse University Archivist Internship Program, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 28)
- Staff Meeting, Mondays, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Alternatives for Contacting EAERP: Populations and Longitudinal Study, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 30)
- Transcription: Travel Budget Projections, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 31)
- Transcription Options (Box 1, Folder 32)
- Interviewing Questions, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 33)
- Research Analysis Notes and Codes, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 34)
- Guideline Questions, EAERP, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 35)
- Research Questions, EAERP, 1987 (Box 1, Folder 36)
- Theoretical Background, EAERP and Historical Perspective (Box 1, Folder 37)
- Qualos Trip, Syracuse University, 1988 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  October 5 1988
- Cultures, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 39)
- Smithers' Endowment Proposal Level I, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 40)
- EAERP Longitudinal Study (Box 1, Folder 41)
- New York City, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 42)
- Albany, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 43)
- Buffalo, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 44)
- Rochester, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 45)
- Syracuse, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 46)
- Westchester, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 47)
- Master File, Non-EAERP Projects, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 48)
  July 24 1990
- Toward a Theory of Organizational Socialization (Box 1, Folder 49)
  Meanen and Schein
- Main Codes, 1990 (Box 1, Folder 50)
- Transcriptions, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 51)
- Research Impressions, 1989 (Box 1, Folder 52)
- Supervisory Training Transcription, 1988-1989 (Box 1, Folder 53)
- EAP Core Elements, 1988-1991 (Box 1, Folder 54)
- Quantitative Analysis, Articles, 1983-1991 (Box 1, Folder 55)
- A2L3R5 (Box 2, Folder 1)
- A5I5R5 (Box 2, Folder 2)
- A6I6R5 (Box 2, Folder 3)
- A8I8R5 (Box 2, Folder 4)
- B1L4R3 (Box 2, Folder 5)
- B2L4R1 (Box 2, Folder 6)
- B3L4R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  June 22 1988
- B4L4R1, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 8)
- B5L4R1, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  June 21 1988
- B6L4R3 (Box 2, Folder 10)
- B7L4R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 11)
- B8L4R6 (Box 2, Folder 12)
- B9L4R3 (Box 2, Folder 13)
- B10L4R1 (Box 2, Folder 14)
- B12L4R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  July 15 1988
- B11L4R1 (Box 2, Folder 16)
- B13L4R1, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 17)
- B14L4R3 (Box 2, Folder 18)
- B15L4R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 19)
- B16L4R3, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 20)
- B17L4R6 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  Thursday July 14
- C1L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 22)
- C3L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 23)
- C4L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 24)
- C5L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  January 21
- C6L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 26)
- C7L3R3 (Box 2, Folder 27)
- D1L1R3, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 28)
  January 5 1987
- D2L1R1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 29)
  September 29 1986
- D5L1R1 (Box 2, Folder 30)
- D6L1R1, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 31)
  January 21 1987
- D7L1R1 (Box 2, Folder 32)
- D3L1R2 (Box 2, Folder 33)
- D4L1R4 (Box 2, Folder 34)
- D8L1R1 (Box 2, Folder 35)
- D9L1R1, 1986 (Box 2, Folder 36)
  August 13 1986
- E1L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 37)
  May 19 1989
- E2L5R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 38)
  May 18 1989
- E3L5R2 (Box 2, Folder 39)
- E4L5R6 (Box 2, Folder 40)
- E5L5R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 41)
  May 17 1989
- E6L3R6 (Box 2, Folder 42)
- E7L5R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 43)
- E8L5R2 (Box 2, Folder 44)
- E9L5R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 45)
- E10L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 46)
- E11L5R2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 47)
- E19L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  Thursday, May 18 1989
- E13L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 49)
- E14L5R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 50)
- E15L5R2 (Box 2, Folder 51)
- E16L5R3 (Box 2, Folder 52)
- E17L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 53)
- E18L5R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  July 25 1989
- E19L5R2 (Box 2, Folder 55)
- F1L6R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  December 20 1989
- F2L6R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 57)
- F5L6R2 (Box 2, Folder 58)
- F6L6R2 (Box 2, Folder 59)
- F8L6R2 (Box 2, Folder 60)
- F10L6R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  December 4 1989
- F11L6R2 (Box 2, Folder 62)
- F12L6R6, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  Tuesday, December 19 1989
- F13L6R2 (Box 2, Folder 64)
- F15L6R3, 1989 (Box 2, Folder 65)
- F17L6R3 (Box 2, Folder 66)
- H7L3R2 (Box 2, Folder 67)
- H1L3R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  March 8 1988
- H2L3R1 (Box 2, Folder 69)
- H3L3R2, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  February 11 1988
- H4L3R3, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  February 9 1988
- H6L3R4 (Box 2, Folder 72)
- H8L3R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 73)
- H9L3R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 74)
  February 23 1988
- H11L3R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 75)
  February 19 1988
- H12L3R6, 1988 (Box 2, Folder 76)
  February 22 1988
- Sign-Out Master File, 1987 (Box 2, Folder 77)
  August 18 - October 6 1987
- I9L1R3, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  December 22 1986
- I10L1R1 (Box 3, Folder 2)
- I11L1R3 (Box 3, Folder 3)
- K1L1R4 (Box 3, Folder 4)
- K2L4R1 (Box 3, Folder 5)
- K3L4R1 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- K4L4R2, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  April 14 1988
- K5L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 8)
- K6L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 9)
- K7L4R3 (Box 3, Folder 10)
- N1L2R1, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  October 11 1988
- N2L2R2 (Box 3, Folder 12)
- N3L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 13)
- N4L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 14)
- N5L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 15)
- N6L2R1, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  May 3 1988
- N7L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 17)
- N8L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 18)
- N9L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 19)
- N10L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 20)
- N11L2R2 (Box 3, Folder 21)
- N12L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 22)
- N13L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 23)
- N15L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 24)
- N16L2R2 (Box 3, Folder 25)
  June 10, year unknown
- N17L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 26)
- N18L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 27)
- O1L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 28)
- O2L2R1 (Box 3, Folder 29)
- O3L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 30)
- O5L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 31)
- O9L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- O10L2R3 (Box 3, Folder 33)
- O11L2R2, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 34)
- O12L2R3, 1987 (Box 3, Folder 35)
  March 25 1987
- P1L5R3, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 36)
  September 19 1988
- P3L5R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 37)
  August 25 1988
- P4L5R3, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 38)
  September 28 1988
- Q1L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 39)
  April 15 1988
- Q2L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 40)
- Q3L4R6 (Box 3, Folder 41)
- Q4L4R1 (Box 3, Folder 42)
- Q5L4R2, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 43)
  April 13 1988, 9:00 a.m.
- Q7L4R3, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 44)
  July 14 1988
- Q8L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 45)
  June 8 1988
- Q9L4R3 (Box 3, Folder 46)
- Q10L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 47)
- Q11L4R3 (Box 3, Folder 48)
- Q12L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 49)
- Q13L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 50)
  June 23 1988
- Q14L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 51)
  April 13 1988
- Q15L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 52)
- Q16L4R6, 1988 (Box 3, Folder 53)
  June 7 1988
- S2L1R2, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 54)
  July 8 1986
- S2L1R2, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 55)
- S3L1R3, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 56)
- S4L1R1 (Box 3, Folder 57)
- S5L1R1 (Box 3, Folder 58)
- S6L1R1, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 59)
  July 16 1986
- S7L1R1, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 60)
  July 7 1986
- S8L1R2, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 61)
- S9L1R1 (Box 3, Folder 62)
- S10L1R1 (Box 3, Folder 63)
- S11L1R2 (Box 3, Folder 64)
  July 11, year unknown
- S12L1R1, 1986 (Box 3, Folder 65)
  Transcribed December 1 and 30 1986
- S13L1R1 (Box 4, Folder 1)
- S14L1R1, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  August 1 1986
- S15L1R1 (Box 4, Folder 3)
- S16L1R1, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  July 9 1986
- S19l1R1 (Box 4, Folder 5)
- S18L1R1, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  Transcribed January 4 1986
- S19L1R1 (Box 4, Folder 7)
- S20L1R1 (Box 4, Folder 8)
- T1L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 9)
- T2L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 10)
- T3L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 11)
- T4L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 12)
- T5L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 13)
- T6L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 14)
- T7L2R3 (Box 4, Folder 15)
  Thursday March 26, New York City. Year Unknown.
- T8L2R3 (Box 4, Folder 16)
  Wednesday march 25
- T9L2R2 (Box 4, Folder 17)
- T10L2R2 (Box 4, Folder 18)
- T11L2R2, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 19)
  October 4 1988
- T13L2R7 (Box 4, Folder 20)
- T14L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 21)
- T15L2R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 22)
  June 16 1988
- T16L2R3 (Box 4, Folder 23)
- T17L2R2, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 24)
  June 8 1987
- T18L2R1 (Box 4, Folder 25)
- T19L2R1, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 26)
  March 10 1987
- T20L2R1, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 27)
  March 12 1987
- V2L3R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 28)
  January 12 1988
- V3L3R6 (Box 4, Folder 29)
- V4L3R1, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 30)
- V5L3R2, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 32)
- V6L3R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 33)
  January 7 1988
- V8L3R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 34)
  February 15 1988
- W1L5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 35)
  Tuesday, August 23 1988
- W2L5R6, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 36)
  July 20 1989
- W3L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 37)
  August 24 1988
- W4L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 38)
  August 23 1988
- W5l5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 39)
  October 14 1988
- W6L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 40)
- W7L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 41)
- W8L5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 42)
- W9L5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 43)
  September 29 1988
- W10L5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 44)
- W11L5R6, 1989 (Box 4, Folder 45)
  July 21 1989
- W12L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 46)
  September 26 1988
- W13L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 47)
- W14L5R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 48)
- W15L5R6 (Box 4, Folder 49)
  Tuesday August 23
- W16L5R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 50)
  Wednesday, August 24 1988
- X1A7R3, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 51)
  December 18 1987
- X2A7R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 52)
  January 27 1988
- X3A1R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 53)
  January 6 1988
- X4A1R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 54)
  January 11 1988
- X5A1R3 (Box 4, Folder 55)
- X6A1R1, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 56)
  March 11 1988
- X7A2R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 57)
  March 31 1988
- X8A2R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 58)
- X9A2R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 59)
  March 9 1988
- X10A3R1 (Box 4, Folder 60)
- X11A2R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 61)
- X12A1R6, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 62)
  June 3 1988
- X13A8R3, 1988 (Box 4, Folder 63)
  March 28 1988
- X50A3R6 (Box 4, Folder 64)